Sacred Heart Church (Notre Dame, Ind.) Records
University of Notre Dame Archives
Sacred Heart Church (Notre Dame, Ind.) Records
1830-1980s
SHC
Sacred Heart Church (Notre Dame, Ind.)
9 linear inches 2 reels microfilm
University of Notre Dame Archives Notre Dame, Indiana 46556
Legal Status
Private
Administrative Information
Sacred Heart Church, Notre Dame, Indiana
Scope and Content
Sacramental and miscellaneous records of Sacred Heart Church and some of the early missionary activity in Northern Indiana and Southwestern Michigan, especially Bertrand and Niles; baptismal, marriage, burial, and dispensation records (1830-1910); records of confraternities and spiritual favors and indulgences established at Sacred Heart (1850s-1960s); a few subject files; and a collection of near-print mailings, reports, bulletins, and lists generated by Sacred Heart Parish (mainly early 1970s).
University of Notre Dame. Church of the Sacred Heart.; Sacred Heart Church (Notre Dame, Ind.)
Related Material
Emily M. Schossberger Papers
- Sacred Heart Church (Notre Dame, Ind.): Manuscripts, CSHC
  - Sacramental Records, CSHC 1/01
    - Father Granger's Baptismal Register, 1842-1857; CSHC 1/01; A transcription, in Father Granger's hand, of the baptismal portion of the register at MSHC #3.7. The transcription is on microfilm at MSHC #2.092+.
  - Subject Files, CSHC 1/02-09
    - Book of Church Services, 1869-1887; CSHC 1/02; Record of church services held at Notre Dame dated 1 January 1869 - 25 December 1887. The book is in the hand of Fr. Alexis Granger and includes information on the dates and times of services, who and how many attended, what sacraments were conferred, descriptive comments, the names of celebrants and important participants, problems encountered, etc.
    - Music Book for Church Organ, 18__; CSHC 1/03; Mss book of organ music in the keys of B and G. The book is entitled "Church Quarters Organ" but there is no indication on the document itself that it belonged in Sacred Heart Church.
    - First National Congress of Religious of the US, 1952; CSHC 1/04; Sacristan Brother Boniface C.SS.R.'s correspondence concerning Mass preparations and clippings concerning the Congress.
    - Pastor Villaflor, 1930-1943; CSHC 1/05; Clippings regarding Pastor Villaflor (the first Filipino to become a United States citizen) and his needlework/ embroidery; and a letter received by Villaflor from his nephew in the Philippines dated 19 June 1947 regarding land titles and the state of the Philippines after World War II.
    - Giuseppe da Copertino, CSHC 1/06; Copies of printed matter and art re St Giuseppe da Copertina; and a certificate (in Latin) authenticating a relic (1954).
    - Edward W. Henricks, 1920/1028; CSHC 1/07; A letter requesting his baptismal record.
    - Obituaries of James E. Bresette, 1935?; CSHC 1/08; Obituaries of one of the first whites Baptised at Notre Dame.
    - Miscellaneous Clippings and Printed, 1800s,1900s; CSHC 1/09; Primarily concerns Saint Bernadette, the Grotto, the Lourdes Centennial at Notre Dame, and miscellaneous topics.
  - Confraternities, Spiritual Favors, and Indulgences, 1850s-1960s; CSHC 1-2/
    - Confraternities at Sacred Heart Church, 18__; CSHC 1/10; Lists the Confraternities at Notre Dame and describes the Spiritual Favors attached to them and to Notre Dame.
    - Miscellaneous Documents re Confraternities, 1800s,1900s; CSHC 1/11; Consists of: [1] membership card for Confraternity Our Lady of Lourdes (19__) [2] printed Prayer for the Adoration of the B.S. (18__). [3] photocopy of Ticket of Admission to the Confraternity of the Immaculate Conception of the Blessed Virgin Mary with explanation of the group (1897/0313). [4] list and description of indulgences and privileges granted by Pius X on 9 November 1911 (dated 26 November 1957).
    - Papal Indulgence, 1876/0418; CSHC 1/12; Handwritten description of a Papal Indulgence for Souls in Purgatory established at Sacred Heart.
    - Archconfraternity Most Holy and Immaculate Heart of Mary, 1839-1956; CSHC 1/13; Five letters in Latin (accompanied by typed calendar entries) regarding the establishment and membership of the Confraternity, a certificate of membership, and two pamphlets concerning the Confraternities purpose and practices, one of which includes a certificate of admission. In English, French and Latin.
    - Association of the Guardian Angels of the Sanctuary, 1876-1886; CSHC 1/14; Pamphlets, enrollment forms, and membership lists.
    - Confraternity of the Holy Rosary Register and Documents, 1893-1961; CSHC 1/15; Consists of a membership register (1893-1924,1961) and loose documents found in the register, consisting of a letter from Reverend Father A. Rooney, O.P. stating conditions for the gaining of indulgences by saying the Rosary, a typed list of names (probably of members) and a pamphlet with information on and a card of membership to the Confraternity.
    - Archconfraternity of Our Lady of Lourdes, 1880s; CSHC 1/16; Two printed items.
    - Confraternity of the Holy Rosary Register, 1891-1897; CSHC 2/01; Lists the names of members.
    - Confraternity of the Nocturnal Adoration, post 1854; CSHC 2/02; A blank membership certificate.
    - Peoples' Eucharistic League / Archconfraternity of the Blessed Sacrament c1910s, CSHC 2/03; Loose papers from the register. Includes several letters from Poirier and others, forms, descriptions of the League, and membership lists.
    - People's Eucharistic League Register / Archconfraternity of the Blessed Sacrament Register, 1911?; CSHC 2/04; This register is blank, but contains spaces for hours of adoration, name, date, and total hours of adoration.
    - Sodality of the Blessed Virgin Mary of Good Counsel, 1885/0521; CSHC 2/05; Document, handwritten in Latin, establishing this group at Notre Dame.
  - Modern Sacred Heart Parish Records, 1960s-1980s; CSHC 3/01-12; Printed and near print materials (and a very few manuscripts) including minutes, lists, reports, descriptions, statements, newsletters, bulletins, mailings, and the like.
    - Parish Council Minutes, 1971-1972; CSHC 3/01
    - Parish Constitutions, 1974; CSHC 3/02
    - Parish Council Steering Committee, 1970; CSHC 3/03
    - Parish Council General and Miscellaneous, 1971-1972; CSHC 3/04
    - Printed Material re Duties, etc. of Parish Councils, 1967-1970; CSHC 3/05
    - Lists of Parishioners, 1960s-1970s; CSHC 3/06
    - Christian Education Commission / Committee, 1970s; CSHC 3/07
    - Christian Service Commission / Committee, 1970s; CSHC 3/08
    - Social Activities Commission / Committee, 1970s; CSHC 3/09
    - Spiritual Development Commission / Committee, 1970s; CSHC 3/10
    - Newsletters and Weekly Bulletins, 1960s-1970s; CSHC 3/11
    - Mailings to Parishoners, 1960s-1980s; CSHC 3/12
- Sacred Heart Church (Notre Dame, Ind.): Microfilm, MSHC
  - Sacramental Records, MSHC #1-5
    These registers generally contain most or all of the following information: date of sacrament, name of recipient, age, place of residence, parents' names, celebrant's name(s), place that the sacrament was administered, sponsor(s)' name(s), and birth or death date. Generally, the entries are in Latin.
    The originals of almost all the microfilmed records are still in the possession of the Basilica. Reels 1-2 were microfilmed by Frank Clark; the quality of these films varies. Reels 3-5, which were filmed in March 1989 by the Geological Society of Utah (their reels #1617238-#1617240), contain many of the same documents and are of consistently good quality. Note that items 1-3 on reel #3 and items 3-7 on reel #5 are records of churches in South Bend and are described in MPIC.
    - "Father Badin's" Baptismal Register, 1830-1841; MSHC #2.063+; The original is in Badin Papers (CZCF).
    - Baptismal Register, 1830/07 - 1844/05; MSHC #3.4; Handwritten transcriptions of "Father Badin's Baptismal Register" (original in Badin's Papers -- CZCF -- and parts of Sacramental Register, Mission Churches Attended From Notre Dame (item 5 below). Duplicated at 3 MSHC #1.013+.
    - Sacramental Register, Missions Attended From Notre Dame, 1841-1847; MSHC #3.5; The title of the volume (appearing on a typed label) reads "Baptismal and Other Records, Bertrand, Niles, etc., 1841-47". There are sections for baptisms, confirmations, marriages, burials, pew rents, and minutes. Arranged by section and then by date. Duplicated at 3 MSHC #1.043+.
    - Baptismal Register (1842/12 - 1857/12) and Marriage Register (1850/01 - 1851/12), 1842-1857; MSHC #3.7; The few pages of marriages come at the end of the volume. Duplicated by #1.142+.
    - Father Granger's Baptismal Register, 1842-1857; MSHC #2.092+; A transcription, in Father Granger's hand, of the baptismal portion of the above register. On paper: CSCH 1/01 (listed above).
    - Baptismal Register, 1858/01 - 1910/12; MSHC #4.3
    - Baptismal Register [transcript], 1858/01 - 1910/12; MSHC #4.4; The second volume is a transcription (in slightly different form) of item 3, above. These two volumes are duplicated on 3 MSHC #1.070+ and 3 MSHC #1.105+.
    - Baptismal Register. 401 pps., 1910/12 - 1948/12; MSHC #4.8; An index appears at the front of the volume.
    - Confirmation Register (1845/01 - 1857/08) and Confirmation Register (1858/03 - 1886/05), 1845-1886; MSHC #3.10; The first register is duplicated at 3 MSHC #2.042+, the second at 3 MSHC #2.050+.
    - Marriage Dispensation Register, 1844/02 - 1857/06; MSHC #3.9; Duplicated at 3 MSHC #1.173+.
    - Marriage Register, 1843/01 - 1856/12; MSHC #3.8; A list of names appears at the front of the volume. Duplicated at 3 MSHC #1.178+.
    - Marriage Register, 1857/01 - 1909/11; MSHC #4.2; Duplicated at 3 MSHC #1.188+.
    - Marriage Register (160 pps.), 1911/05 - 1932/06; MSHC #5.1; An index appears at the front of the volume.
    - Death Register, 1844/04 - 1856/12; MSHC #3.6; Duplicated at 3 MSHC #1.205+.
    - Death Register, 1857/01 - 1910/09; MSHC #4.1; Duplicated at 3 MSHC #2.011+.
    - Death Register (87pps.), 1911/04 - 1989/01; MSHC #5.2
    - Baptismal Register, Saint Mary's College (16pps.), 1890/05 - 1958/06; MSHC #4.5; Arranged roughly by date. An index appears at the front. This is a register for baptisms at St Mary's College, but the relationship to the Church of Our Lady of Loretto is unclear.
    - item 7 - First Communion Register, Saint Mary's College, 1898/06 - 1961/03; MSHC #4.7; An index appears at the front of the volume. This is a register for first communions at St Mary's College, but the relationship to the Church of Our Lady of Loretto is unclear.
    - Confirmation Register, Saint Mary's College (23+ pps.), 1891/05 - 1954/04; MSHC #4.6; An index appears at the front of the volume. Also includes lists of persons enrolled in the Scapular (1953/05 - 1960/03) and three baptisms (1946-1947) at the end of the volume. This is a register for confirmations at St Mary's College, but the relationship to the Church of Our Lady of Loretto is unclear.
- Sacred Heart Church (Notre Dame, Ind.): Printed Material, PSHC
  Parish bulletins, 1998-present, and other parish printed material.